Chapter 2. Fire on the mountain. By the time Ralph finished blowing the conchk, the platform was
crowded. There were differences between this meeting and the one held in the
morning. The afternoon sun slanted in from the other side of the platform, and
most of the children, feeling too late the smart of sunburn, had put their
clothes on. The choir, noticeably less of a group, had discarded their cloaks.
Ralph sat on a fallen trunk, his left side to the sun. On his right were most
of the choir. On his left, the larger boys, who had not known each other
before the evacuation. Before him, small children squatted in the grass. Silence
now. Ralph lifted the cream and pink shell to his knees, and a sudden breeze
scattered light over the platform. He was uncertain whether to stand up or
remain sitting. He looked sideways to his left toward the bathing pool. Piggy
was sitting near, but giving no help.
Ralph cleared his throat. Well then, all at once, he found he could talk fluently
and explained what he had to say. He passed a hand through his bare hair and
spoke. We're on an island. We've been on the mountaintop and seen water all
round. We saw no houses, no smoke, no footprints, no boats, no people. We're
on an uninhabited island with no other people on it. Jack broke in. All the
same, you need an army for hunting.
Hunting pigs? Yes, there are pigs on the island. All three of them tried to
convey the sense of the pink live thing struggling in the creepers. We saw
squealing. It broke away before I could kill it. But next time, Jack slammed his
knife into a trunk and looked round challengingly. The meeting settled down
again. So you see, said Ralph, we need hunters to get us meat. And another
thing. He lifted the shell on his knees and looked around the sun slashed faces.
There aren't any grown-ups. We shall have to look after ourselves. The
meeting hummed and was silent. And another thing, we can't have everybody
talking at once. We'll have to have hands up like at school. He held the
conchk before his face and glanced around the mouth. Then I'll give him the
conchk. Conchk? That's what this shell is called. I'll give the conchk to the
next person to speak. He can hold it when he's speaking. But look, and he
won't be interrupted except by me. Jack was on his feet. We'll have rules, he
cried excitedly. Lots of rules. Then when anyone breaks them, we oh wacko
bong doink. Ralph felt the conchk lifted from his lap. Then Piggy was standing,
cradling the great cream shell, and the shouting died down. Jack, left on his
feet, looked uncertainly at Ralph, who smiled and patted the log. Jack sat
down. Piggy took off his glasses and blinked at the assembly while he wiped
them on his shirt. You're hindering Ralph. You're not letting him get to the
most important thing. He paused effectively. Who knows we're here, eh?
They knew at the airport. The man with the trumpet thing, my dad. Piggy put on
his glasses. Nobody knows where we are, said Piggy. He was paler than before and
breathless. Perhaps they knew where we was going to. And perhaps not. But they
don't know where we are cuz we never got there. He gaped at them for a moment,
then swayed and sat down. Ralph took the conchk from his
hands. That's what I was going to say, he went on. When you all all He gazed at
their intent faces. The plane was shot down in flames. Nobody knows where we
are. We may be here a long time. The silence was so complete that they could
hear the unevenness of Piggy's breathing. The sun slanted in and lay
golden over half the platform. The breezes that on the lagoon had chased
their tails like kittens were finding their way across the platform and into
the forest. Ralph pushed back the tangle of fair hair that hung on his forehead.
So, we may be here a long time. Nobody said anything. He grinned suddenly. But
this is a good island. We, Jack, Simon, and me. We climbed the mountain. It's
wizard. There's food and drink and rocks, blue flowers. Piggy, partly
recovered, pointed to the conchk in Ralph's hands, and Jack and Simon fell
silent. Ralph went on. While we're waiting, we can have a good time on this
island. He justiculated wildly. It's like in a book. At once, there was a
clamor. Treasure Island, swallows and Amazon, Coral Island. Ralph waved the
conchk. This is our island. It's a good island. Until the grown-ups come to
fetch us, we'll have fun. Jack held out his hand for the conchk. There's pigs,
he said. There's food and bathing water in that little stream along there and
everything. Didn't anyone find anything else? He handed the conchk back to Ralph
and sat down. Apparently, no one had found anything. The older boys first
noticed the child when he resisted.
There was a group of little boys urging him forward, and he did not want to go.
He was a shrimp of a boy, about 6 years old, and one side of his face was
blotted out by a mulberryc colored birthark. He stood now, warped out of
the perpendicular by the fierce light of publicity, and he bored into the coarse
grass with one toe. He was muttering and about to cry. The other little boys,
whispering, but serious, pushed him toward Ralph. All right, said Ralph.
Come on then. The small boy looked round in panic. Speak up. The small boy held out
his hands for the conchk, and the assembly shouted with laughter. At once
he snatched back his hands and started to cry. Let him have the conchk, shouted
Piggy. Let him have it. At last Ralph induced him to hold the shell, but by
then the blow of laughter had taken away the child's voice. Piggy knelt by him,
one hand on the great shell, listening and interpreting to the assembly. He
wants to know what you're going to do about the snake thing. Ralph laughed,
and the other boys laughed with him. The small boy twisted further into himself.
Tell us about the snake thing. Now he says it was a beastie. Beasty? A snake
thing? Ever so big? He saw it. Where? In the woods. Either the wandering breezes
or perhaps the decline of the sun allowed a little coolness to lie under
the trees. The boys felt it and stirred restlessly. "You couldn't have a beasty,
a snake thing on an island this size," Ralph explained kindly. "You only get
them in big countries like Africa or India." Murmur and the grave nodding of
heads. He says the beastie came in the dark. Then he couldn't see it. Laughter
and cheers. Did you hear that? Says he saw the thing in the dark. He still says
he saw the beastie. It came and went away again and came back and wanted to
eat him. He was dreaming. Laughing, Ralph looked for confirmation around the ring of faces.
The older boys agreed, but here and there among the little ones was the
doubt that required more than rational assurance. He must have had a nightmare.
Stumbling about among all those creepers, more grave nodding. They knew
about nightmares. He says he saw the beastie, the snake thing, and will it
come back tonight? But there isn't a beastie.
He says in the morning it turned into them things like ropes in the trees and
hung in the branches. He says, "Will it come back tonight?" But there isn't a
beastie. There was no laughter at all now and more grave watching. Ralph
pushed both hands through his hair and looked at the little boy in mixed
amusement and exasperation. Jack seized the conchk. Ralph's right. Of course,
there isn't a snake thing. But if there was a snake, we'd hunt it and kill it.
We're going to hunt pigs to get meat for everybody. And we'll look for the snake,
too. But there isn't a snake. We'll make sure when we go hunting. Ralph was
annoyed and for the moment defeated. He felt himself facing something
ungraspable. The eyes that looked so intently at him were without humor. But
there isn't a beast. Something he had not known was there rose in him and
compelled him to make the point loudly and again. But I tell you, there isn't a
beast. The assembly was silent. Ralph lifted the conchk again, and his good
humor came back as he thought of what he
had to say next. Now we come to the most important thing. I've been thinking. I
was thinking while we were climbing the mountain. He flashed a conspiratorial
grin at the other two and on the beach just now. This is what I thought. We
want to have fun and we want to be rescued. The passionate noise of
agreement from the assembly hit him like a wave and he lost his thread. He
thought again. We want to be rescued and of course we shall be rescued. Voices
babbled. The simple statement unbacked by any proof but the weight of Ralph's
new authority brought light and happiness. He had to wave the conchk
before he could make them hear him. My father's in the Navy. He said there
aren't any unknown islands left. He says the queen has a big room full of maps
and all the islands in the world are drawn there. So the queen's got a
picture of this island. Again came the sounds of cheerfulness and better
heart. And sooner or later a ship will put in here. It might even be daddy's
ship. So you see sooner or later we shall be rescued. He paused with the
point made. The assembly was lifted toward safety by his words. They liked
and now respected him. Spontaneously they began to clap and presently the
platform was loud with applause. Ralph flushed looking sideways at Piggy's open
admiration and then the other way at Jack who was smirking and showing that
he too knew how to clap. Ralph waved the conchk. Shut up. Wait, listen. He went
on in the silence born on his triumph.
There's another thing. We can help them to find this. If a ship comes near the
island, they may not notice us. So, we must make smoke on top of the mountain.
We must make a fire. A fire. Make a fire. At once, half the boys were on
their feet. Jack clammered among them.
the conchk forgotten. Come on, follow me. The space under the palm trees was
full of noise and movement. Ralph was on his feet, too, shouting for quiet, but
no one heard him. All at once, the crowd swayed toward the island and was gone,
following Jack. Even the tiny children went and did their best among the leaves
and broken branches. Ralph was left holding the conchk with no one but
Piggy. Piggy's breathing was quite restored. "Like kids," he said
scornfully, "acting like a crowd of kids." Ralph looked at him doubtfully
and laid the conchk on the tree trunk.
"I bet it's gone tea time," said Piggy.
What do they think they're going to do on that mountain? He caressed the shell
respectfully, then stopped and looked up. Ralph, hey, where are you going?
Ralph was already clambering over the first smashed swats of the scar. A long
way ahead of him was crashing in laughter. Piggy watched him in disgust
like a crowd of kids. He sighed, bent, and laced up his shoes. The noise of the
errant assembly faded up the mountain.
Then with the martyed expression of a parent who has to keep up with the
senseless abulance of the children, he picked up the conchk turned toward the
forest and began to pick his way over the tumbled scar. Below the other side
of the mountaintop was a platform of forest. Once more Ralph found himself
making the cupping gesture. Down there we could get as much wood as we want.
Jack nodded and pulled at his underlip.
Starting perhaps 100 ft below them on the steeper side of the mountain. The
patch might have been designed expressly for fuel. Trees forced by the damp heat
found too little soil for full growth.
fell early and decayed. Creepers cradled them, and new saplings searched a way
up. Jack turned to the choir, who stood ready. Their black caps of maintenance
were slid over one ear like berets.
"We'll build a pile. Come on." They found the likeliest path down and began
tugging at the dead wood, and the small boys who had reached the top came
sliding, too, till everyone but Piggy was busy. Most of the wood was so rotten
that when they pulled, it broke up into a shower of fragments and wood lice and
decay. But some trunks came out in one piece. The twins, Sam and Eric, were the
first to get a likely log, but they could do nothing till Ralph, Jack,
Simon, Roger, and Maurice found room for a handhold. Then they inched the
grotesque dead thing up the rock and toppled it over on top. Each party of
boys added a quot less or more, and the pile grew. At the return, Ralph found
himself alone on a limb with Jack, and they grinned at each other, sharing this
burden. Once more, amid the breeze, the shouting, the slanting sunlight on the
high mountain, was shed that glamour, that strange invisible light of
friendship, adventure, and content.
Almost too heavy, Jack grinned back. Not for the two of us. Together, joined in
an effort by the burden, they staggered up the last steep of the mountain.
Together they chanted, "One, two, three," and crashed the log onto the
great pile. Then they stepped back, laughing with triumphant pleasure, so
that immediately Ralph had to stand on his head. Below them, boys were still
laboring, though some of the small ones had lost interest and were searching
this new forest for fruit. Now the twins, with unsuspected intelligence,
came up the mountain with armfuls of dried leaves and dumped them against the
pile. One by one, as they sensed that the pile was complete, the boys stopped
going back for more and stood with the pink shattered top of the mountain
around them. Breath came evenly by now, and sweat dried. Ralph and Jack looked
at each other while society paused about them. The shameful knowledge grew in
them, and they did not know how to begin confession. Ralph spoke first, crimson
in the face. Will you? He cleared his throat and went on. Will you light the
fire? Now the absurd situation was open.
Jack blushed too. He began to mutter vaguely. You rub two sticks. You rub. He
glanced at Ralph, who blurted out the last confession of incompetence. "Has
anyone got any matches?" "You make a bow and spin the arrow," said Roger. He
rubbed his hands in mime. A little air was moving over the
mountain. Piggy came with it in shorts and shirt, laboring cautiously out of
the forest with the evening sunlight gleaming from his glasses. He held the
conchk under his arm. Ralph shouted at him, "Piggy, have you got any matches?"
The other boys took up the cry till the mountain rang. Piggy shook his head and
came to the pile. "My, you've made a big heap, haven't you?" Jack pointed
suddenly. "His specks! Use them as burning glasses!" Piggy was surrounded
before he could back away. "Here, let me go!" His voice rose to a shriek of
terror as Jack snatched the glasses off his face. "Mind out! Give them back.
back. I can hardly see. You'll break the conchk. Ralph elbowed him to one side
and knelt by the pile. Stand out of the light. There was pushing and pulling and
a fish officious cries. Ralph moved the lenses back and forth. This way and
that, till a glossy white image of the declining sun lay on a piece of rotten
wood. Almost at once, a thin trickle of smoke rose up and made him cough. Jack
knelt too and blew gently so that the smoke drifted away, thickening, and a
tiny flame appeared. The flame, nearly invisible at first in that bright
sunlight, enveloped a small twig, grew, was enriched with color, and reached up
to a branch, which exploded with a sharp crack. The flame flapped higher, and the
boys broke into a cheer. "My specks!"
howled Piggy. "Give me my specks." Ralph stood away from the pile and put the
glasses into Piggy's groping hands. His voice subsided to a mutter. "Just blurs,
that's all. Hardly see my hand." The boys were dancing. The pile was so
rotten and now so tinder dry that whole limbs yielded passionately to the yellow
flames that poured upwards and shook a great beard of flame 20 ft in the air.
For yards round the fire, the heat was like a blow, and the breeze was a river
of sparks. Trunks crumbled to white dust. Ralph shouted, "More wood! All of
you get more wood." Life became a race with the fire, and the boys scattered
through the upper forest. To keep a clean flag of flame flying on the
mountain was the immediate end, and no one looked further. Even the smallest
boys, unless Fruit claimed them, brought little pieces of wood, and threw them
in. The air moved a little faster and became a light wind, so that leird and
windward side were clearly differentiated. On one side, the air was
cool, but on the other, the fire thrust out a savage arm of heat that crinkled
hair on the instant. Boys who felt the evening wind on their damp faces paused
to enjoy the freshness of it, and then found they were exhausted. They flung
themselves down in the shadows that lay among the shattered rocks. The beard of
flame diminished quickly. Then the pile fell inwards with a soft cindery sound
and sent a great tree of sparks upwards that leaned away and drifted downwind.
The boys lay panting like dogs. Ralph raised his head off his forearms. That
was no good. Roger spat efficiently into the hot dust. What do you mean? There
wasn't any smoke, only flame. Piggy had settled himself in a space between two
rocks and sat with the conchk on his knees. We haven't made a fire, he said.
What's any use? We couldn't keep a fire like that going. Not if we tried. A fat
lot you tried, said Jack contemptuously.
You just sat. We used his specs, said Simon, smearing a black cheek with his
forearm. He helped that way. I got the conchk, said Piggy indignantly. You let
me speak. The conchk doesn't count on top of the mountain, said Jack. So you
shut up. I got the conchk in my hand.
Put on green branches, said Maurice.
That's the best way to make smoke. I got the conchk, Jack turned fiercely. You
shut up. Piggy wilted. Ralph took the conchk from him and looked around the
circle of boys. We've got to have special people for looking after the
fire. Any day there may be a ship out there. He waved his arm at the tot wire
of the horizon. And if we have a signal going, they'll come and take us off. And
another thing, we ought to have more rules. Where the conchk is, that's a
meeting the same up here as down there.
They ascented. Piggy opened his mouth to speak, caught Jack's eye, and shut it
again. Jack held out his hands for the conchk and stood up, holding the
delicate thing carefully in his study hands. I agree with Ralph. We've got to
have rules and obey them. After all, we're not savages. We're English and the
English are best at everything. So, we've got to do the right things. He
turned to Ralph. Ralph, I'll split up the choir, my hunters that is, into
groups, and we'll be responsible for keeping the fire going. This generosity
brought a spatter of applause from the boys, so that Jack grinned at them, then
waved the conchk for silence. We'll let the fire burn out now. Who would see
smoke at nighttime anyway, and we can start the fire again whenever we like.
Altos, you can keep the fire going this week, and trebles the next. the assembly
asented gravely. And we'll be responsible for keeping a lookout, too.
If we see a ship out there, they followed the direction of his bony arm
with their eyes. We'll put green branches on. Then there will be more
smoke. They gazed intently at the dense blue of the horizon, as if a little
silhouette might appear there at any moment. The sun in the west was a drop
of burning gold that slid nearer and nearer the sill of the world. All at
once they were aware of the evening as the end of light and warmth. Roger took
the conchk and looked round at them gloomily. I've been watching the sea.
There hasn't been the trace of a ship.
Perhaps we'll never be rescued. A murmur rose and swept away. Ralph took back the
conchk. I said before we'll be rescued sometime. We've just got to wait, that's
all. Daring, indignant, Piggy took the conchk. That's what I said. I said about
our meetings and things, and then you said shut up. His voice lifted into the
wine of virtuous recrimination. They stirred and began to shout him down. You
said you wanted a small fire, and you been built a pile like a hay rick. If I
say anything, cried Piggy with bitter realism, you say shut up. But if Jack or
Maurice or Simon, he paused in the tumult, standing, looking beyond them,
and down the unfriendly side of the mountain to the great patch where they
had found dead wood. Then he laughed so strangely that they were hushed, looking
at the flash of his spectacles in astonishment. They followed his gaze to
find the sour joke. "You've got your small fire all right." Smoke was rising
here and there among the creepers that foned the dead or dying trees. As they
watched, a flash of fire appeared at the root of one wisp, and then the smoke
thickened. Small flames stirred at the trunk of a tree and crawled away through
leaves and brushwood, dividing and increasing. One patch touched a tree
trunk and scrambled up like a bright squirrel. The smoke increased, sifted,
rolled outwards. The squirrel leapt on the wings of the wind and clung to
another standing tree, eating downwards.
Beneath the dark canopy of leaves and smoke, the fire laid hold on the forest
and began to gnaw. Acres of black and yellow smoke rolled steadily toward the
sea. At the sight of the flames and the irresistible course of the fire, the
boys broke into shrill, excited cheering. The flames, as though they
were a kind of wild life, crept as a jaguar creeps on its belly toward a line
of birch-like saplings that fledged an outcrop of the pink rock. They flapped
at the first of the trees, and the branches grew a brief foliage of fire.
The heart of flame leapt nimly across the gap between the trees, and then went
swinging and flaring along the whole row of them. Beneath the capering boys, a
quarter of a mile square of forest was savaged with smoke and flame. The
separate noises of the fire merged into a drum roll that seemed to shake the
mountain. "You got your small fire all right." Startled, Ralph realized that
the boys were falling still and silent, feeling the beginnings of awe at the
power set free below them. The knowledge and the awe made him savage. "Oh, shut
up." "I got the conchk," said Piggy in a hurt voice. "I got a right to speak."
They looked at him with eyes that lacked interest in what they saw and cocked
ears at the drum roll of the fire. Piggy glanced nervously into hell and cradled
the conchk. We got to let that burn out now. And that was our firewood. He
licked his lips. There ain't nothing we can do. We ought to be more careful. I'm
scared. Jack dragged his eyes away from the fire. You're always scared.
Fatty. I got the conchk, said Piggy bleakly. He turned to Ralph. I got the
conchk, ain't I, Ralph? Unwillingly, Ralph turned away from the splendid,
awful sight. What's that? The conchk. I got a right to speak. The twins giggled
together. We wanted smoke. Now look. A paw stretched for miles away from the
island. All the boys except Piggy started to giggle. Presently they were
shrieking with laughter. Piggy lost his temper. I got the conchk. Just you
listen. The first thing we ought to have made was shelters down there by the
beach. It wasn't half cold down there in the night, but the first time Ral says
fire, you goes howling and screaming up this here mountain, like a pack of kids.
By now, they were listening to the tirade. How can you expect to be rescued
if you don't put things first things first and act proper? He took off his
glasses and made as if to put down the conchk, but the sudden motion toward it
of most of the older boys changed his mind. He tucked the shell under his arm
and crouched back on a rock. Then, when you get here, you build a bonfire that
isn't no use. Now, you've been set the whole island on fire. Won't we look
funny if the whole island burns up?
Cooked fruit. That's what we'll have to eat. And roast pork and that's nothing
to laugh at. You said Ralph was chief and you don't give him time to think.
Then when he says something, you rush off like like He paused for breath and
the fire growled at them. And that's not all. Them kids, the little onins. Who
took any notice of him? Who knows how many we got? Ralph took a sudden step
forward. I told you to. I told you to get a list of names. How could I? Cried
Piggy indignantly. All by myself. They waited for 2 minutes, then they fell in
the sea. They went into the forest. They just scattered everywhere. How was I to
know which was which? Ralph licked pale lips. Then you don't know how many of us
there ought to be. How could I with them little running around like insects? Then
when you three came back, as soon as you said make a fire, they all ran away, and
I never had a chance. That's enough, said Ralph sharply, and snatched back
the conchk. If you didn't, you didn't.
Then you come up here and pinch my specks. Jack turned on him. You shut up.
and them little ends was wandering about down there where the fire is. How do you
know they aren't still there? Piggy stood up and pointed to the smoke and
flames. A murmur rose among the boys and died away. Something strange was
happening to Piggy, for he was gasping for breath. "That little!" gasped Piggy.
"Him with the mark on his face. I don't see him. Where is he now?" The crowd was
as silent as death. Him that talked about the snakes. He was down there. A
tree exploded in the fire like a bomb.
Tall swaths of creepers rose for a moment into view, agonized, and went
down again. The little boys screamed at them. "Snakes! Snakes! Look at the
snakes!" In the west, and unheated, the sun lay only an inch or two above the
sea. Their faces were lit redly from beneath. Piggy fell against a rock and
clutched it with both hands. "That little had a mark on his face. Where is
he now? I tell you, I don't see him."
The boys looked at each other fearfully, unbelieving. "Where is he now?" Ralph
muttered the reply as if in shame.
Perhaps he went back to the the beneath them on the unfriendly side of the
mountain. The drum roll continued. Lord of the